Okay בוקר טוב *Boker Tov*. So today's דף *daf* is ל"ב *Lamed
Beis*, 32, and we pick up near the bottom, at the bottom
of ל"א Lo, עמוד ב' *Lamed Aleph Amud Beis*, three lines in,
and we're moving on from the various invalidities of the לולב Lulav
*Lulav*. We did גזול *Gazul* and יבש *Yavesh*, two of the big
ones. גזול *Gazul* had all issues of ownership and מצוה הבאה בעבירה
Mitzvah haba'ah ba'aveirah? *Mitzvah Ha'ba'ah B'aveirah* possibilities. יבש
*Yavesh* got into a whole central discussion of the requirement of הדר
hadar *Hadar*, of beautiful, that comes from אתרוג ethrog, *Esrog* but is
applied to the ארבע מינים arba minim *Arba Minim*. רבי יהודה *Rabbi
Yehuda* being in the end of the conclusion of the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* rejects the requirement of הדר *Hadar* both by לולב lulav *Lulav*
and by אתרוג etrog *Esrog*. Even אתרוג *Esrog* where it's located, although
has other criteria that are not rooted in הדר *Hadar* and might
be in the fullness of the fruit and other types that it's
a fully developed fruit and other criteria. And finally, the other important
issue came down was the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that spoke about בקפיפין
*B'kafiffin*, dried up לולבים lulavim *Lulavim*, and presumably making a ברכה berachah
*bracha* on them and the Rabbis said אין שעת הדחק ראיה *Ein
Sha'as Ha'dechak Ra'aya*, which raised questions in the ראשונים Rishonim *Rishonim* of
whether aren't other options can you actually use invalid ארבע מינים minim
*Arba Minim* and make a ברכה bracha *bracha* on them, would that
be a comparison to the שעת הדחק *Sha'as Ha'dechak* of the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*. Now we move on from גזול *Gazul* and יבש *Yavesh*
to the other invalidities, and the next is also the question of
אשרה Asherah? ועיר הנדחת *Asheira Ve'ir Nidachas*. Let's take a look. Three
lines down in the wide lines. של אשרה Asherah? ושל עיר הנדחת
ir hanidachat *Shel Asheira Veshel Ir Nidachas*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says if it's of an אשרה Asherah *Asheira*, which is a tree
that is worshiped, and an עיר הנדחת ir hanidachat, *Ir Nidachas*, which
is a city that the people in the city worshiped עבודה זרה
Avodah Zarah *Avodah Zarah* and then you have to destroy and burn
the whole city. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says של אשרה Asherah.
פסול pasul, *Shel Asheira Pasul*. Is that of an אשרה Asherah *Asheira*
invalid? והאמר רבא Rava *Veha'amar Rava*, רבא Rava *Rava* said לולב lulav
של עבודה זרה avodah zarah, *Lulav Shel Avodah Zarah*, a לולב lulav
*Lulav* of idolatry לא יטול Lo Yitol, *Lo Yitol*, do not take
it, ואם נטל כשר Ve'im Natal Kasher. *Ve'im Natal Kasher*, and if
you took it, it is כשר kasher. *Kasher*. Now what does it
mean it is of עבודה זרה avodah zarah, *Avodah Zarah*? So could
be you worshiped the לולב lulav, *Lulav*. רש"י Rashi *Rashi* gives two
other possibilities. If you take a look at רש"י Rashi *Rashi*, לולב
lulav של עבודה זרה avodah zarah, *Lulav Shel Avodah Zarah*, about ten
lines down in the narrow lines, ששימשו בו לעבודה זרה לכבד לפניה
קרקע *Sheshimeshu Bo L'avodah Zarah L'chabed Lefaneha Karka*. You use it as
a broom to sweep in front of the עבודה זרה avodah zarah,
*Avodah Zarah*. That is a category called תשמישי עבודה זרה Tashmishei Avodah
Zarah *Tashmishei Avodah Zarah*, something that is an appurtenance, something that is
used to serve. Now I want to be clear, עבודה זרה avodah
zarah *Avodah Zarah* does not mean an idolatrous religion in this context.
עבודה זרה avodah zarah *Avodah Zarah* means an object, an idol that
was worshiped. The principle is whatever you say about the prohibitions of
worshiping עבודה זרה avodah zarah *Avodah Zarah* and so on, that's one
thing, and what constitutes a religion of עבודה זרה avodah zarah *Avodah
Zarah* that it's forbidden to worship in that religion, but there's another
consideration which is our focus here, which is when worship is directed
towards an object, that object becomes an idol and that object becomes
forbidden in הנאה Hana'ah, *hana'ah*, forbidden in benefit. And then the question
is what are the other types of things that are connected to
the object, not—this is what the meaning of עבודה זרה avodah zarah.
*Avodah Zarah* here is in this context—idol, so that they also are
forbidden in הנאה Hana'ah. *hana'ah* by extension. Okay, so I want that
to be clear. It's not just that you used something
like if somebody goes ahead and signs, I don't know, a hymnbook
from
a Hindu hymnbook, okay, and you decide Hindu is definitely עבודה זרה
avodah zarah, *Avodah Zarah*, so a Hindu hymnbook doesn't mean that it's
תשמישי עבודה זרה avodah zarah *Tashmishei Avodah Zarah*. The question is for
איסור הנאה Hana'ah. *Issur Hana'ah*, was this object used in connection with
an idol because the idol is forbidden in benefit and things that
are connected to that idol by extension also become forbidden benefit. So
if you use this לולב lulav *Lulav* to sweep in front of
an idol, then it's תשמישי עבודה זרה avodah zarah, *Tashmishei Avodah Zarah*
and is forbidden in benefit.
ההוא בשייטלאך *Hahu B'sheitlach* that came from India,
that's what that was about. אי נמי *Ee Nami*, שעבודתה בלולב להעביר
לפניה ולזרקה בה *She'avodatah B'lulav L'ha'avir Lefaneha Ul'zorkah Bah*. You actually used
this לולב lulav *Lulav* in a worship in front of the idol.
Again, not just in a worship of an idolatrous religion, but you
used it in front of the idol. So you did a whole
לולב lulav *Lulav* dance in front of the idol, and that makes
it forbidden. That's called a different principle which is תקרובת עבודה זרה
avodah zarah. *Tikroves Avodah Zarah*, actually it's still תשמישי *tashmishei*, תקרובת *tikroves*
is actually if it's offered up as an offering to the עבודה
זרה avodah zarah *Avodah Zarah*. So anyway, that is how it becomes
forbidden, that it is used in some type of a service in
front of the idol. I should say by the
way that yes, in fact if basically somebody slaughtered an animal and
offered it up to Zeus, so even if there's no idol around,
that's also forbidden because of תקרובת עבודה זרה avodah zarah, *Tikroves Avodah
Zarah*, then it becomes an offering to a pagan god and so
on, so things that are actually offered
up. So if you have a לולב lulav that is this thing
that is either worshipped and forbidden in benefit or תשמישי עבודה זרה
avodah zarah. and forbidden in benefit, and you go ahead and use
it on סוכות, Sukkot, so לא יטול, don't take it. Why shouldn't
you take it? Because it's, you might say it's forbidden in הנאה,
Hana'ah you're getting benefit from it, but let's read the next line.
ואם נטל כשר. Ve'im Natal Kasher. But if you took it, you
actually were יוצא Yotzei your מצוה. Mitzvah. Now how were you יוצא
Yotzei your מצוה? Mitzvah? Isn't it forbidden in benefit? So this then
becomes the very classic principle of מצוות לאו ליהנות ניתנו. Mitzvot Lav
Lehenot Nitnu. מצוות Mitzvot are not given for הנאה. Hana'ah? What does
that mean? It means there's a רש"י Rashi, somewhere that says that
what it means is, actually this רש"י Rashi says it here as
well. He says it in different places, different ways. Look at רש"י,
Rashi ואם נטל כשר. kasher רש"י Rashi says: ואף על גב דאיסורא
דהנאה הוא, Ve'af Al Gav De'isura De'hana'ah Hu, even though it's forbidden
benefit, דמצוות לאו ליהנות ניתנו. Demitzvot Lav Lehenot Nitnu. כלומר, Kelomar, what
that means is, אין קיום מצוות הנאת הגוף, Ein Kiyum Mitzvot Hana'at
Ha'guf, doing a מצוה Mitzvah is not a benefit to the body,
אלא עבודת עבד לרבו. Ela Avodat Eved L'rabo. It is the service
of a servant to his master. Now in other places רש"י Rashi
says even stronger, something like מצוות Mitzvot weren't given for your benefit.
מצוות Mitzvot were given לעול צוואריהם ניתנו, Le'ol Tzavareihem Nitnu, to be
a yoke on your
necks. So it's a little bit different than the רב חנניה בן
עקשיא אומר רצה הקדוש ברוך הוא לזכות את ישראל. Rav Chananya Ben
Akashya Omer Ratza Hakadosh Baruch Hu Lezakot Et Yisrael. So sometimes רש"י
Rashi interprets מצוות לאו ליהנות ניתנו Mitzvot Lav Lehenot Nitnu as you
shouldn't experience מצוות Mitzvot as giving you religious fulfillment or whatever. No,
you do it out of a sense of service. It's
a very harsh type of an approach. The simple explanation has nothing
to do with whether we enjoy or don't enjoy giving מצוות Mitzvot
and whether we think theologically God gave it to us so that
it should be for our benefit etc. The simple point is a
very nuts and bolts הלכתית Halachic point, which is הלכה Halacha deals
with physical realities, not with metaphysical realities. And if something is forbidden
in benefit, benefit is measured by
this worldly benefit. Otherworldly benefit is not relevant for the realm of
הלכה. Halacha. And again that's pretty surprising, הלכה Halacha is religious law,
but one of the I think surprising and beautiful things about הלכה
Halacha is how
grounded it is and how much it is like if you want
to measure something, you measure it by the this worldly reality of
it. So even if you have enormous benefit in עולם הבא, Olam
Ha'ba, that is not how you measure benefit and therefore it's not
considered to be הנאה. hana'ah. Now I suppose a question would be
okay, that's in terms of what reward God will give me in
the future. But let's say I enjoy doing a מצוה, Mitzvah, you
know, I get personal satisfaction.
Why isn't enjoyment a type of a pleasure? Which is interesting questions,
but I'll just give you for example another case. You know, if
you go to watch a movie or you go to
an art gallery and you see this beautiful thing, let's say at
the art gallery you look at עבודה זרה avodah zarah. and you
get all this aesthetic pleasure. So technically that's also not אסור בהנאה.
Assur Be'hana'ah. Rabbinically it is, but not biblically because it is not
a physical pleasure and that it's a more aesthetic pleasure. That's the
principle called
כל קול ומראה וריח אין בהם משום מעילה. Kol Kol U'mareh V'reiach
Ein Bahem Mishum Me'ilah. Aesthetic visual or sound, those types of pleasures
are not considered technically really forbidden pleasures. Now again rabbinically it's an
issue. It gets to whole questions about using a dead body
for medical knowledge. Things that are benefits but not in a way
physical benefits. The גמרא Gemara, has the issue about smell because smell
is much more a physical thing than
vision or things like aesthetic pleasure and so on. So that's the
principle of מצוות לאו ליהנות ניתנו. Mitzvot Lav Lehenot Nitnu. The otherworldly
benefits you get from them, even this sort of satisfaction you get,
that doesn't count as benefit within the world of הלכה. Halacha. הלכה
Halacha is very this worldly and that is not a type of
a concrete physical this worldly benefit. So therefore although it's forbidden in
הנאה and you shouldn't take it, if you took it you're יוצא
Yotzei the מצוה. Mitzvah. You did not transgress, you did not derive
benefit. So then of course the question is so why is it
forbidden in הנאה? Why shouldn't I take it? I mean why shouldn't
I take it if I'll be יוצא Yotzei the מצוה? Mitzvah? So
there רש"י Rashi just says in like two words דמאיס לגבוה. Dema'is
Ligvoah. It's still disgusting. You don't want to use something associated with
idolatry to do a מצוה Mitzvah to God. But even though it's
disgusting, technically if you did it you'd be יוצא. Yotzei. And that's
the principle. So then the question is so why aren't you יוצא
Yotzei with a לולב lulav of an אשרה? Why don't we say
the same thing? Don't do it, it's disgusting to use it, but
if you did it it's not considered benefit and you should be
יוצא. Yotzei. So before we get to the answer, I just want
to point out that an obvious question to ask here is: wait
a minute, it's more than just disgusting. Shouldn't this be מצוה הבאה
בעבירה? Mitzvah haba'ah ba'aveirah. You did the עבירה, aveirah, you worshipped עבודה
זרה, avodah zarah, shouldn't that invalidate or somebody worshipped עבודה זרה, avodah
zarah, shouldn't that invalidate this object and make this object unusable for
a מצוה? mitzvah? Right? Pretty reasonable question. It should be more than
disgusting, it should be unusable. Forget הנאה. It's worshipped, it was worshipped.
So תוספות Tosafot asks this earlier in the סוגיא sugya of מצוה
הבאה בעבירה. Mitzvah haba'ah ba'aveirah And he says two things. And basically,
תוספות's Tosafot answer is that, yes, you did an עבירה, aveirah, but
that עבירה aveirah was completely unrelated to the מצוה. mitzvah. He says,
let's say you used this לולב lulav to dig a hole on
שבת. Shabbat. Would it not be able to use it for a
מצוה? mitzvah? Let's say you carried the לולב lulav into רשות הרבים
reshut harabim on שבת. Shabbat. Would you not be able to use
it? So similarly, if you worshipped the עבודה זרה, avodah zarah this
as עבודה זרה, avodah zarah you did a big עבירה, aveirah, but
it doesn't make it's not that the מצוה mitzvah comes through the
עבירה. aveirah. When you steal it, the stealing enabled you to do
the מצוה. mitzvah. But when you worshipped it, that was unrelated to
the מצוה. mitzvah. So that's how תוספות Tosafot explained it. I still
have to say, all of that being said, if the problem of
מצוה הבאה בעבירה Mitzvah haba'ah ba'aveirah when we learned it was not
just that the action focused, that the action of the עבירה aveirah
enabled the action of the מצוה mitzvah is intertwined with it, but
if the idea, if you remember we discussed, was that it somehow
disqualifies the object, stigmatizes the object, it would seem to me, maybe
carrying a לולב lulav. into רשות הרבים reshut harabim doesn't stigmatize the
object, but it would seem to me worshipping something for עבודה זרה
avodah zarah should put it totally off the table for using it
for מצוות. mitzvot. It should be more than just מאיס. ma'is. Something
that's used for another religion should be
disqualified for being used in a מצוה mitzvah context. So it still
is pretty shocking that the גמרא Gemara does not make this a
מצוה mitzvah. הבאה בעבירה problem. But תוספות Tosafot focuses not on the
object but on the action and says, yeah, but the action did
not enable the מצוה. mitzvah So now we're going to have to
say, here's our issue. The לולב, lulav, don't use it, it's disgusting,
but if you did use it, you're יוצא, yotzei, it's not considered
benefit. So why does our משנה Mishnah say you can't use a
לולב lulav of אשרה? How is that any different than this case?
Charlie, what do you want to say?
So an example where the עבירה aveirah causes it to be available
might be when there was a temple, if you carried your לולב
lulav through the רשות הרבים reshut harabim on שבת Shabbat on the
first day.
Right, if you weren't able to get but if it was only
well, it wouldn't be because then you could have done it at
home, but you're saying let's say it was on חול המועד Chol
HaMoed where only מצוות mitzvot taking it was in the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash and then you something else, whatever.
But another question philosophically, there actually are some מצוות mitzvot in the
תורה Torah where the תורה Torah itself gives some examples of actual
benefit.
What do you mean? Oh, like God will give you
compassion and those types of things?
Yeah, but again,
that's not something that can be counted on and this is not
like a real physical concrete type of a thing, it's a divine
promise. That gets into the metaphysical realm. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara,
says like this.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, so how do you
explain why an אשרה is invalid? Shouldn't it be that don't do
it, but if you do it, it's okay? So the גמרא Gemara
says, no, הכא באשרה דמשה עסקינן. hacha b'Asherah d'Moshe askinan. We're talking
about משה's Moshe אשרה. דכתותי מכתת שיעוריה d'chitutei mechatat shiurei and its
size is completely ground up. I'll just read this and then unpack
it.
דיקא נמי דקתני דומיא דעיר הנדחת deika nami d'katani dumya d'ir hanidachat
that it says it's similar to the idea of a condemned city.
שמע מינה. shma mina. That's a good proof. Well, that was self-explanatory.
So
the point is the following. There's a principle called כתותי מכתת שיעוריה
chitutei mechatat shiurei which means something that there is a מצוה mitzvah.
to destroy, it's like it's already burnt and destroyed and cannot be
used for a מצוה. mitzvah Now, it doesn't have to mean you
literally look at it like a pile of ashes, although there are
some גמרות Gemarot that sound like that. But what it could just
mean is that the מצוה mitzvah to destroy it undermines any of
its significance and therefore it can't have the weight of being used
as a מצוה mitzvah object. If you think about it, the whole
idea of a שיעור shiur is to say it has to be
a minimum size or
minimum whatever quantity in order to be significant. Well, if the whole
idea is to destroy it, that completely undermines the sense of any
significance of this object. So something that there's a מצוה mitzvah to
destroy cannot be used as a מצוה mitzvah. object because of this
idea of כתותי מכתת שיעוריה. chitutei mechatat shiurei. So that is the
reason why the עיר הנדחת ir hanidachat is no good. The עיר
הנדחת, Ir Nidachat, the לולבים lulavim in the city of the עיר
הנדחת ir ha'nidachat were not used in any forbidden thing. But because
those לולבים lulavim, will have to be destroyed and burnt, they can't
be used. Similarly, says the גמרא, Gemara the אשרה here, the problem
is not that it's forbidden in benefit. The issue is, what's another
thing that's a הלכה halacha of עבודה זרה in addition to the
fact that you can't get benefit from it of an idol? What
do you have to do with idols? You have to destroy them.
So if it's something that is not... forbidden in benefit, but has
to be destroyed, then it's like the עיר הנדחת, and then you
can't use it for the מצוה. mitzvah Okay, that makes a lot
of sense, but what do you mean by Moshe's אשירה? Asherah? The
גמרא Gemara seems to be distinguishing that there are two categories of
idols, idols that have to be destroyed and idols that don't have
to be destroyed. And the idols that have to be destroyed are,
ironically, called Moshe's אשירות. Asheras. So what do you mean by Moshe's
אשירות? Asheras? So let's take a look at what רש״י Rashi says
about this, באשירה דמשה. ba-Asherah de-Moshe.
רש״י Rashi says the following: אותם שהיו בשעת כיבוש ארץ ישראל, otam
she-hayu bi-sha'at kibbush Eretz Yisrael,
those that were at the time when Israel was conquered, שהצריכן הכתוב
שריפה, she-hitzrichan ha-katuv sereifah, that they had to be burnt, כדכתיב ואשריהם
תשרפון באש. ki-de-chtiv va-ashereihem tisrefun ba-esh. ולולב צריך שיעור והאי כמאן דמכתת
שיעוריה. ve-lulav tzarich shi'ur ve-hai ke-man de-miktat shi'ureih. So
רש״י Rashi seems to say, very shocking רש״י, Rashi, seems to say
the only עבודה זרה that there's a מצוה mitzvah to destroy is
the עבודה זרה that was in the land of Israel when they
entered into conquer the land. But after the period of משה רבינו,
Moshe Rabbeinu, by the way I don't know why it doesn't say
אשירה דיהושע, Asherah de-Yehoshua, but okay, after the period of משה רבינו,
Moshe Rabbeinu, there's no מצוה mitzvah to destroy עבודה זרה. Now I
have to say something about this because, you know, normally like nobody
ever says that. The תורה Torah just says destroy it and the
general assumption in, you know, the פוסקים poskim and the ראשונים is
it's a מצוה mitzvah to destroy עבודה זרה, doesn't matter where and
when. And that leads, so, but the point is, here's a shocking
thing. If you read through all of the משניות Mishnayot and all
of the גמרות Gemarot about עבודה זרה and there's tons, and there's
a whole מסכת עבודה זרה Masechet Avodah Zarah and all these types
of things, you will see discussion about יין נסך, yayin nesech, you
will see discussions about things that are אסור בהנאה assur be-hana'ah because
they were used in עבודה זרה, you will see discussions about forbidden
worship and what constitutes forbidden worship. You know which one thing you
won't see? A discussion of the מצוה mitzvah to destroy עבודה זרה.
It's not there. Why not? Scholars have said, well think about it
for a minute. The משניות Mishnayot were being written in the land
of Israel under Roman rule, which was filled with pagan idols. You
cannot go about discussing the מצוה mitzvah to destroy עבודה זרה and
to be in that type of reality. So it was just sort
of, you know, it was just like bracketed. It wasn't discussed. So
that's quite fascinating and it's fascinating because in contemporary times right now,
you know, you have some people talking about well how do we
allow this in the land of Israel and that in the land
of Israel, there's a מצוה mitzvah to destroy עבודה זרה, you're not
allowed to allow עובדי עבודה זרה ovdei avodah zarah in the land
and so on. It's interesting to note that some that those things
that were completely impractical at the time the משנה Mishnah was being
discussed were bracketed. And רש״י Rashi here actually makes it הלכה halachically
bracketed because this רש״י Rashi seems to say that actually the only
מצוה mitzvah to destroy was at the time of יהושע, Yehoshua, at
the time that they conquered the land. After then there's no מצוה
mitzvah to destroy, which is a quite a fascinating רש״י. Rashi. תוספות
Tosafot does not say that. תוספות Tosafot says that the difference of
which you have a מצוה mitzvah to destroy and which you don't
have a מצוה mitzvah to destroy is, he says Moshe refers to
like Jewish עבודה זרה. And he says there's a difference between Jewish
and non-Jewish עבודה זרה. Why? Because he says if a non-Jew worships
עבודה זרה, an idol, a non-Jew can also annul it, be מבטל
mevattel it, and say I no longer treat this as an idol,
throw it in the trash can, and then it becomes permissible. But
as soon as it is worshipped or owned by a Jew, its
status cannot change. And therefore תוספות Tosafot says that's the difference. If
it still can be un-בטל, battel, you know, or un-עבודה זרה, it
could be nullified, right, then
it's not considered like it's destroyed and burnt up because it might
its status might change. All you have to do is the non-Jew
just has to discard it. But once there's no other alternative, once
it will never change its status and it has to be destroyed,
then you can't use it because of this principle of מכתת שיעוריה.
miktat shi'ureih.
Yeah, I was teaching in a high school yesterday the first משנה
Mishnah in the ninth chapter of ברכות Berachot about the
ברכה of נעקרה עבודה זרה במקום
הזה.
ne'ekrah avodah
zarah be-makom hazeh. Yeah. And the student said is it possible that
the פשט pshat of that משנה Mishnah could be that it's talking
about the עבודה זרה that's worshipped by Jews as an act of
disloyalty and that that משנה Mishnah is not talking about the עבודה
זרה of a non-Jew?
Could be. I don't know. I mean it's a lot of discussion.
That's not how I normally understood it, but it could be.
Right, in light of what you just said.
Right. Okay, so that is the conclusion of the גמרא, Gemara. that
if it were just forbidden in benefit and worshipped, that would not
be enough, quite shocking, even though stolen is enough to disqualify. But
if it's a מצוה to destroy it, because of רש״י's Rashi's you
know that it was עבודה זרה in the time of משה, Moshe,
more literally or יהושע, Yehoshua, or תוספות Tosafot that it's owned by
a Jew and cannot be have its status removed and therefore it
must be destroyed, then it is not valid because it's like it
is already burnt up. So we go from those fascinating discussions now
back to some aesthetic issues and more concrete physical issues. So let's
take a look. נקטם ראשו, niktam rosho, if the head of the
לולב lulav is cut off, it's not good. אמר רב הונא, Amar
Rav Huna, לא שנו אלא נקטם, lo shanu ela niktam, that's only
if it's cut off. אבל נסדק, Aval nisdak, if
it
is
split, כשר. kasher. if you look at רש״י Rashi נשתקו ראשי העלים,
nishteku rashei ha’alim, maybe many of the leaves are split. So again,
not, I’m not going to get into how this translates into practical
הלכה halacha because there’s a million discussions of, you know, debates about
exactly which physical, you know, what aspect of the לולב lulav. it’s
talking about. But let’s just go see what it says. So if
the leaves are split as opposed to cut off, that’s okay. And
the גמרא Gemara,
says ונסדק כשר? ve’nistak kasher? Split leaves okay? והתניא ve’tanya we learned
in a ברייתא, braita, לולב כפוף lulav kafuf if you have a
לולב lulav, that’s bent over, קווץ kavatz or whatever if it’s thorny,
סדוק saduk if it’s split, עקום דומה למגל akum domeh lemagal or
it’s so sort of bent that it’s like a scythe, right? So
that’s really a big bent, פסול, pasul it’s invalid. חרות, charut, if
it is like hard like a stick, right? You know sometimes the
leaves get so hard it becomes like a stick, פסול pasul. that’s
invalid. דומה לחרות domeh lecharut if they’re if it’s starting to harden
but the leaves are still separable, then כשר kasher it’s kosher. Okay,
so the bent and the hard we sort of get, that’s, you
know, obviously not הדר and not what a לולב lulav is supposed
to look like. It doesn’t have separate leaves, it’s not straight and
so on. But how about this issue
about, it’s by the way, the idea that if it has thorns
coming out of the side it’s invalid is also interesting. But okay,
all of that we get, but one thing we’re going to focus
on is this issue about סדוק saduk split. So you see, and
you said that split was okay? So אמר פפא Amar Papa דעביד
כהמניק. de’avid kehemnek. No,
when it’s split is no good, we’re talking about that it’s very
seriously split, which is that it’s basically like if you look at
the רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel you have a picture, this is apparently
before the age of Xerox machines, the way you did a, you
didn’t have to copy things twice, is you had a pen that
had two tips to it. So you would basically write once and
you sort of see how that would work. You had a thing
with like two separate tips and you had one piece of paper
here and one piece of paper here and you sort of like
wrote once, you know, it would come out as there would be
two, there would be two copies. You could also do three copies
depending on how you had the whole thing structured. Anyway, sometimes you
see this in some of those movies that try to depict ancient
times, you see people doing that. Anyway, so if it’s really totally
split, like the שדרה shidra separates off into two separate heads, that’s
no good. But if you just have that the leaves are split
down, that’s not a problem. Okay, so that’s a, that’s a pretty
nice leniency. Let’s see how the גמרא Gemara continues. עקום דומה למגל,
akum domeh lemagal, what about if it’s bent over like a scythe,
it’s no good? You know very often a לולב lulav. does have
a bent, I mean normally not like a scythe, but it’s normally
that it does have a bent. So אמר רבא Amar Rava לא
אמרן אלא לפניו. lo amran ela lifanav. The only problem is if
it’s bent, it’s sort of in front of it, you know, if
you consider the שדרה shidra of the לולב lulav. the back and
the other part the front, so if it’s bent down facing the
front. אבל לאחריו בריה היא, aval le’achorav briya hi, but if it’s
bent back towards the spine, that’s like a natural shape of the
לולב. lulav Now is that really true? Because I think when I
buy לולבים, lulavs. right? And I hold them by the שדרה shidra
and I sort of look straight to see how straight they are,
you know, when they bend they tend to bend down, right? They
don’t bend up against the spine. Isn’t that right? They bend down,
right? So I’m not exactly sure what this means, that when he
says that when it’s backwards towards the spine it’s the normal way.
Maybe it means like if it’s a serious bend, but I don’t
know. I mean, do they have any pictures there or any descriptions
in any of that, no? All right, so I don’t know exactly
what that means. אמר רב נחמן Amar Rav Nachman לצדדין כלפניו דמי,
litzadin kilifanav dami, if it bends over to the side, that’s like
in front of it and that’s no good. ואמרי לה כלאחריו דמי,
ve’amri lah kelachorav dami, and some say no, that’s like bent back
and that is good. Okay, so we don’t know what the story
is if it bends too much to one side or another. This
is a question in general as I said when you buy a
לולב, lulav how much does it have to be like ramrod straight?
How much can it, you know, be a little bit bent? So
I try to get mine, you know, very very straight, but the
question always becomes how bent is bent and how much is it
a problem? And also this גמרא Gemara with its difference of לפניו
lifanav and לאחריו, le’achorav, you know, makes also like how how to
exactly apply that. ואמר רבא ve’amar Rava האי לולבא דסליק בחד הוצא,
hai lulava desalik bechad hutza, if you have a לולב lulav. that
all the leaves come out on only one side of the spine,
בעל מום הוא פסול, ba’al mum hu pasul, that’s like a blemished
לולב lulav and it’s פסול. pasul. Again, not like it’s in the
משנה, Mishna, but you sort of see that if you have a
general aesthetic issue of aesthetics, what exact things violate a minimum aesthetics
is, you know, is like a judgment call. So like the fact
that the גמרא Gemara threw in the idea that it had spines,
well we weren’t even thinking about that, that should invalidate. So here
רבא Rava is talking about something which maybe would have been been
more obvious, you know, that all of the leaves are coming out
on only one side. Okay, so that’s the types of bends and
of the לולב lulav and the split of the לולב.
lulav Now we get a feature here it has to have symmetry.
Symmetry, right.
Right, exactly. It can't all be. So I think that that's actually
a good point, you know, in the sort of in the whole
sort of science of aesthetics or you know, study of aesthetics, which
I don't really know, but obviously I do know going back to
Aristotle the importance of symmetry is a very central concept to aesthetics.
So that is true and that comes about all things, the אתרוג,
the לולב, lulav you know, you want them to look symmetrical. That's
the basic thing. So that's a very good way of pointing out
the problem here about coming out on one side. Okay, נפרצו עליו,
nifretsu alav, so the משנה Mishna says if the leaves were, were
like נפרט, nifrat, which is separated off, it's invalid. נפרדו, nifredu, if
they're spread out, it's כשר. kasher, So what נפרדו nifredu is talking
about is not hard to understand. It means that the leaves are
like fanned out, they're all connected to the spine but they're fanned
out and that's why רב יהודה Reb Yehuda says oh, it might
be כשר kasher. but you have to flatten them against the
spine. But what is נפרצו? nifretsu? What scenario is נפרצו nifretsu that
it's invalid? So רשי Rashi, says it means that the leaves actually
fell off the לולב lulav. and you rebind them to the spine
of the לולב. lulav You know, תוספות Tosafos feels like that's way
too obvious to be saying that that's invalid and anyway, תוספות Tosafos
understands that נפרצו nifretsu means that all of the leaves have opened
up. You know, you know the leaves are double leaves? So it
means all of the leaves have basically been opened up and that
that would be the case of נפרדו. nifredu. So let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara Of נפרצו, nifretsu, excuse me, נפרצו nifretsu
which is invalid. אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Pappa, נפרצו, nifretsu, נפרצו
nifretsu which is invalid, דעביד כחופיא, de'avid ke'hufya, it's like a broom.
So what does that mean a broom? So רשי Rashi says what
do you do with a broom? You have all of the leaves
fell off and you tie it back up as a you know,
and that's what makes it like a broom. תוספות Tosafos says no,
if the leaves have been split open and are you know, open
faced, that makes it more you know, broom-like. So a whole debate
about what this case is, but if it's like a broom then
it's invalid. נפרדו nifredu when it's okay, דאיפרוד איפרודי, de'ifrud i'frudei, they're
fanned out but they're still all connected to the spine and it's
just that they've fanned out and that's actually okay. So בעי רב
פפא, ba'ei Rav Pappa, רב פפא Rav Pappa asked, נחלקה
התיומת מהו? nechleka hatayomes mahu? Okay, this is probably the most important
question that we get by shopping for a לולב. lulav If the
tip of it is split, what's the story? Interesting, although we said
before that you know, split leaves are not a problem but unless
it's made like a you know like a two separate spines. Okay,
a normal split leaf is not a problem. But what about the
tip of it? What's the story there? Okay, so he says נחלקה
התיומת מהו, nechleka hatayomes mahu, what's the story if the tip of
it is split? So תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear, דאמר
רבי יוחנן de'amar Reb Yochanan ואמרי לה רב מתנא, ve'somrei Rav Matna,
אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, amar Reb Yehoshua ben Levi, נטלה התיומת
פסול. nitlah hatayomes pasul. If the tip is removed, it's invalid. מאי
לאו הוא הדין נחלקה? Mai lav hu hadin nechleka? Wouldn't it be
the same whether it's removed or if it's split? לא,
no. נטלה שאני, Nitlah shani, if it's removed it's different, דחסר ליה,
de'chasar lei, it's actually missing, that's a bigger problem. איכא דאמרי, Ika
de'amrei, so according to that if a split top would not be
a problem. איכא דאמרי, Ika de'amrei, others say, אמר רבי יוחנן amar
Reb Yochanan או o אמר רב מתנא, amar Rav Matna, אמר רבי
יהושע בן לוי, amar Reb Yehoshua ben Levi, נחלקה התיומת, nechleka hatayomes,
if the top is split, נעשה כמי שנטלה התיומת ופסול, na'aseh kemi
shenitlah hatayomes u'pasul, it's as bad as it being removed and it's
invalid. So this becomes the biggest issue for לולב lulav because we
said before that a normal splitting of leaves is not a problem.
Okay, just think about the three things we just said. A normal
splitting of leaves is not a problem, good. Bending could be a
problem, but how much bent and in which direction? So that's a
question. And now we get to the third thing which is the
biggest issue, which is you know people looking at the tip and
making sure the tip isn't split. And the גמרא, Gemara. at least
the second approach of the גמרא Gemara is that a split tip
is no good. So how split? So take a look at רשי,
Rashi רשי Rashi, at least saves us a little bit. רשי Rashi,
says נחלקה
התיומת, nechleka hatayomes, it's about 20 lines down, he says
שני עלים עליונים אמצעיים shenei alim elyonim emtza'iyim ששם השדרה כלה, she'sham
hashidrah kalah, נחלקו זה מזה, nechleku zeh mizeh, they split from one
another, ונסדקה השדרה venisdekah hashidrah עד העלים שלמטה מהם, ad ha'alim shelematta
mehem, and they split all the way down until the leaves below
them. So if you have, I don't again, I'm not sure this
is completely accurate this is from my visual memory of what a
לולב lulav looks like. Okay, you have like the spine here, right,
and then you've got like the leaves like, anyway, at the top,
right, if you've got the spine, right, and then you've got like
the top sort of leaf coming from the spine, and then you've
got these leaves right coming from here, right?
Sort of, you can sort of see what I'm saying.
So according to רשי, Rashi if it's split a little there, it's
not a problem. It has to be split all the way down
until it hits the spine and until it gets to the where
the next leaves come out of the spine from. So according to
that רשי, Rashi right, it's it's rarely a problem. Okay, but for
others even a tiny little split at the top is an issue
and that's why people go crazy, myself included, looking for a לולב.
lulav? Okay, so that is the issue of the תיומת. tayomes. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this: רב יהודה אומר, Rav Yehuda omer,
now רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says, if its leaves are fanned out,
you have to bind them so that they're flat against the spine.
תני, Tani, we taught in a ברייתא, braita, רב יהודה אומר משום
רבי טרפון, Rav Yehuda omer mishum Rabi Tarfon, כפות תמרים, kapot tmarim,
a palm branch, a branch of a palm tree, כפות אם היה
פרוד יכפתנו. kapot im haya parud yichpetenu. כפות Kapot means bound is
a way of reading it. So if they were spread out, you
need to bind them against the spine. אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי,
Amar lei Ravina le-Rav Ashi, so רבינא Ravina said to רב אשי,
Rav Ashi, ממאי דהאי כפות תמרים דלולב הוא? mimai de-hai kapot tmarim
de-lulav hu? How do you know that this whole word כפות תמרים
kapot tmarim means a palm branch? אימא חירותא? Eima cheruta? But what?
How do you know what the words mean? How do you know?
תמר Tamar does mean a palm...
right. תמר Tamar does mean a palm... right. I don't understand. So,
but no, here's the question. I mean I shouldn't have emphasized the
word, you're right. I shouldn't have emphasized the word palm if I
did. It definitely comes from a palm tree. But how do you
know that it is the the the part of the palm tree
where the leaves are separate but flat against the spine? Maybe it
is a different part of the palm tree. Okay? אימא חירותא, Eima
cheruta, but so like we said before, we just spoke about חירותא
cheruta which was when these branches become sticks, right? When you leave
them on the tree long enough, the leaves sort of fuse and
it becomes a stick. So how do you know that it means
separate leaves? Maybe it means when it actually becomes a stick. So
the גמרא Gemara says no, בעינן כפות וליכא. be'inan kaput ve-leika. You
need it to be something that is actually bindable. There has to
be separate leaves so it is actually, you know, something that can
be bound together. According to this, it's just a stick. You wouldn't
call that כפות. kapot. You wouldn't call that something bindable. So the
גמרא Gemara says ואימא אופצלא. ve-eima uptzala. But what about אופצלא? uptzala?
So רש"י Rashi says that that actually is some type of a
thing from like the trunk of the tree, not from a branch.
Fiber of the trunk?
Yeah.
So he
says, okay, where is it? ואימא אופצלא. ve-eima uptzala. So it says
no, כפות מכלל דאיכא פרוד, kaput miklal de-ika parud, ואי האי כפות
וקאי. ve-hai kaput ve-omay. So כפות kaput means that it was something
that was, you know, that... hold on, let me just check רש"י
Rashi a minute.
רש"י Rashi is printed in my book כופרא kufra with
a ר. resh.
No, that's the next question in the גמרא. Gemara Okay, but I...
hold on just one minute. I just want to look at one
thing.
One minute. אופצלא. Uptzala.
Okay, okay, no, no, I... so
okay. Wait, wait. Okay, no, no, I understood... I missed... I misread
the first thing. Let's go back for a minute. Okay? So the
גמרא Gemara says when it says אימא חירותא, eima cheruta, which is
the sticks, it wasn't suggesting the way רש"י Rashi, explains it to
take like a stick all by itself. What it was suggesting was,
you know, if you take the... think about a branch of a
tree, right? So, you know, don't take one of the sticks and
think that these are the לולב lulav branches and they've been on
long enough that they have now hardened. So imagine each one of
these could have been a לולב lulav but now it's hardened. So
these are called חירותא. cheruta. It's when the leaves have fused and
hardened. So take a branch with all of those offshoot חירותא cheruta
and use that. That's separate things, all of the branches essentially that
are offshoots are like they are separate. So the גמרא Gemara says
no, בעינן כפות וליכא. be'inan kaput ve-leika. That's not good because you
need it to be bound up. You need it to be flat
against the spine, so that remains separate. So then says, okay, ואימא
אופצלא. ve-eima uptzala. Now אופצלא uptzala is a part of the trunk
or that actually everything is just one unit. So for that the
גמרא Gemara says no, כפות מכלל דאיכא פרוד, kaput miklal de-ika parud,
bound up means that there are separate elements but they're just situated
all together. So you can't have branches because they are not situated
together. You can't have a stick because a stick doesn't have separate
elements. You need the actual לולב lulav? with the loose leaves that
are against the spine that has both elements: separate units but bound
together. So the גמרא Gemara says ואי האי כפות וקאי, ve-hai kaput
ve-omay, and this sort of stick is always one unit, it's not
separate units bound together. ואימא כופרא? Ve-eima kufra? What about כופרא? kufra?
So רש"י Rashi. says that's a case of like loose branches. Let's
take a look at רש"י, Rashi we'll read רש"י. Rashi ואימא כופרא,
Ve-eima kufra, רש"י Rashi says היינו נמי עץ כעץ חירותא אלא דעדיין
בן שנה או שתי שנים ולא נתעבה עצו ואתה יכול לכפול ענפיו
על ידי אגד. hainu nami etz ke-etz cheruta ela de-adayin ben shana
o shtei shanim velo nitabe itzo ve-ata yachol lichpol anaphav al yedei
agad. So he says it's like this case except they're not
so hard. These things are separate but if you really forced them
you could bring them all together. So maybe it's that case of
the branch with sticks that could be brought together. So the גמרא
Gemara says, אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, דרכיה דרכי נעם וכל נתיבותיה שלום.
deracheha darchei noam vechol nesivoseha shalom. The Torah's ways are pleasant and
beautiful, and these, when it's
at this stage, there's all of these thorns on
the branch, and it'll scratch you, and obviously the Torah would not
want you to do that. כתיב. Kesiv. אמר ליה רבא, Amar lei
Rava, so רבא says, אמר ליה רבא תוספאה לרבינא, Amar lei Rava
Tosfa'ah le-Ravina, so רבא תוספאה Rava Tosfa'ah said to רבינא, Ravina, ואימא
תרתי כפי דתמרי, ve-eima tarti kapei de-timarei, maybe we should take כפות
kapot in the plural, maybe we should take two לולבים. lulavs כפת
כתיב. Kapat kesiv. No, it's written without the ו"ו. vav. ואימא חדא,
Ve-eima chada, so maybe you should take, one minute, oh no, again
I misread it, I'm sorry. רש"י Rashi says תרתי כפי דתמרי tarti
kapei de-timarei means, oh, why not take like a cluster of dates?
Right, maybe כפת תמרים kapat temarim means a cluster of dates? So,
okay, so how do you say because that's separate units, we're talking
here all about branches and whatever and separate units together. I don't
know, to get a cluster of dates like this, right? And here's
your palm branch that they're on, so that cluster are separate things
that are then all together. So maybe, so maybe, maybe it means
take a cluster of grapes—dates. So it says, so
כפת כתיב. kapat kesiv. No, it says כפת kapat in the singular,
which basically means that it has to be, one minute, that it
can only be one. ואימא חדא, Ve-eima chada,
so fine to take one cluster of grape—dates. לאהו כף קרי ליה.
La-hu kaf kari lei. That wouldn't be called כפת, kapat, that would
just be called a כף. kaf. Okay, so because it says כפות
kapot somehow, if it said כפות kapot with a ו"ו, vav, it
would have—it could have meant multiple clusters of grapes, of dates. If
it said כף, kaf, it could have meant one cluster of grapes,
of dates. Somehow since it says כפות kapot in this way, it's
one thing which is many, and what's the one thing which is
many? That's the לולב lulav that basically it's separate leaves but they
all come together for one unit. So this is a very like,
I don't know, frustrating—a little bit frustrating for me because I'm trying
to remember what these physical scenarios are. But anyway, but besides which,
it's like, you know, did the גמרא Gemara really think that the
Torah meant take a cluster of dates? Was that really a serious
הוה אמינא? hava amina? And only because of the yes ו"ו vav
and not the ו"ו vav and all of that, did it figure
out that it was talking about a לולב. lulav So רמב"ם Rambam
in פירוש המשניות Perush Hamishnayot uses this and other גמרות Gemaras that
we're going to see coming up that also try to figure out
what is ענף עץ עבות, anaf etz avot, what is פרי עץ
הדר, pri etz hadar, what are these things? And has similar types
of derivations, well maybe it's this fruit, maybe it's that fruit, and
then comes up with very sort of like weak explanations about how
you know it's exactly this fruit. And רמב"ם Rambam says we have
to assume they just knew this by tradition. You know, how do
you know what any word means, right? So it's obviously there's a
tradition, there's an oral culture, you know, that's passed down about what
these words in the language mean. So רמב"ם Rambam says that's actually,
and this is interesting because we normally don't say—put this in this
category, he says that's actually a form of הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha
le-Moshe mi-Sinai in the sense of that it's not something that is
derived from the verse, it's something we always knew. We always knew,
or there was always a tradition what was meant here. And when
the גמרא Gemara speaks about maybe it's this type of part of
the palm tree and that part of the palm tree, maybe it's
the dates and maybe it's this, it's just doing it like for
fun. It's just doing it to try to show how you can
link it to the verse. But the bottom—bottom line is we know
what it's talking about because there was always a tradition what it
was talking about. Okay, so that's a point that the רמב"ם Rambam
makes in פירוש המשניות. Perush Hamishnayot. Okay, so let's take a look,
we'll see more of that later. ציני הר הברזל כשרה. Tzinei har
habarzel kesherah. Now if a—if a לולב lulav comes from this ציני
tzinei of this iron mountain, then it is כשרה. kesherah. What does
that mean? So let's take a look. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, לא
שנו אלא שראשו של זה מגיע לצד עיקרו של זה אבל אין
ראשו של זה מגיע לצד עיקרו של זה פסול. lo shanu ella
she-rosho shel zeh magi'a le-tzad ikaro shel zeh aval ein rosho shel
zeh magi'a le-tzad ikaro shel zeh pasul. It is a type of
לולב lulav, where the leaves don't actually overlap, where one leaf is
very short and it only comes to the base of the next
leaf. Okay, but that's when it's כשר, kasher? even that is כשר.
kasher, But it is—if it is so small the leaf that the
tip of one leaf does not reach the base of the next,
that's
invalid. תניא נמי הכי וסיימי ליה, Tanya nami hachi ve-siyamei lei, ציני
הר הברזל פסולה. tzinei har habarzel pesulah. It's invalid. והנן תנן כשרה?
Ve-hanan tenan kesherah? המשנה Mishna says
כשר? kasher. אלא שמע מינה כאביי שמע מינה. Ela shema mina ke-Abaye
shema mina. Proof like אביי Abaye's resolution that if the leaf reaches
the base it's כשר, kasher, if it doesn't reach the base of
the next leaf it's invalid. Okay, ואיכא דרמי רמי. ve-ika de-ramei ramei.
Some make it—show it as a contradiction. תנן, Tenan, we learned in
the משנה, Mishna, ציני הר הברזל כשרה. tzinei har habarzel kesherah. It's
כשר. kosher. ותניא פסולה. Ve-tanya pesulah. We taught a ברייתא Baraita it's
invalid. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, so they said that אביי Abaye's teaching
was coming to reconcile the משנה Mishna and the ברייתא. Baraita. לא
קשיא כאן שראשו של זה מגיע לצד עיקרו של זה כאן שאין
ראשו של זה מגיע לצד עיקרו של זה. lo kashya kan she-rosho
shel zeh magi'a le-tzad ikaro shel zeh kan she-ein rosho shel zeh
magi'a le-tzad ikaro shel zeh. When the tip of one leaf reaches
the base of the next it's כשר, kosher. if it doesn't even
reach the base of the next it's invalid. Okay. אמר רבי מריון,
Amar Rabbi Miryon, אמר
רבי יהושע בן לוי, amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, ואמרי לה ve-amrei
lah תני רבה בר מרי Tani Rabba bar Mari משום רבן יוחנן
בן זכאי, mishum Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai, so two interesting different
traditions, שתי תמרות יש בגי בן הינום. shtei tmarot yesh b'gei ben
Hinnom. There are two palm trees in גי בן הינום, Gei Ben
Hinnom, the valley of בן הינום Ben Hinnom which is outside of
ירושלים Yerushalayim but also becomes the source of our concept of גיהנום,
Gehennom, גי בן הינום. Gei Ben Hinnom. Okay. ועולה עשן מביניהם. Ve-ole
ashan mi-beineihem. And smoke rises from between these two palm trees, so
again one wonders about the גיהנום Gehennom association. וזהו ששנינו ציני הר
ברזל זו כשירות. v'zehu she-shaninu tzinei har barzel zu ksheirot. And this
is what is meant by the ציני הר ברזל, tzinei har barzel,
not exactly clear again what those why the iron mountain what that
means, but that's where those palm trees grow that have these shortened
leaves and that's what the משנה mishna is referring to, the palm
trees in this valley of בן הינום. Ben Hinnom. וזהו, v'zehu, and
if the association wasn't clear enough, וזו היא פתחה של גיהנום, v'zo
hi pitcha shel gehennom, in between those palm trees, right where the
smoke is, if you go down and follow the smoke, you'll get
access to גיהנום. Gehennom. So from
the valley of בן הינום Ben Hinnom where the smoke rises, that's
the entryway, the gateway to גיהנום, Gehennom, and you know like sometimes
you have these palm trees like at the sides of an entrance
or archway, so you get the palm trees, the archway to גיהנום,
Gehennom, and those לולבים from those trees actually is כשר. kosher. Okay.
I'm sure you can make a really good דרשה drasha out of
that. Anyway. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel.
Okay. לולב שיש בו שלושה טפחים. Lulav she-yesh bo shlosha tfachim. Now
we get to the size. If it's שלושה טפחים shlosha tfachim the
משנה mishna says enough to shake it, it's כשר. kosher, So what
does this mean? So אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda
amar Shmuel, שיעור הדס וערבה שלושה, shiyur hadas va-arava shlosha, the size
of a הדס hadas and an ערבה arava שלושה shlosha is three
טפחים. tfachim. הלולב ארבעה, ha-lulav arba'a, and a לולב lulav is four
טפחים, tfachim, כדי שיהא לולב יוצא מן ההדס טפח. kedai she-yehei lulav
yotzei min ha-hadas tefach. It should be come up from above, okay,
a whole טפח tefach higher. Interesting he says מן ההדס, min ha-hadas,
not מן הערבה. min ha-arava. Anyway, so this is an idea and
I should reiterate this, you know that the way we have one
אתרוג and the other three מינים minim bound together is because of
the way the פסוק pasuk is written: ולקחתם לכם ביום הראשון פרי
עץ הדר, u-lkachtem lakhem ba-yom ha-rishon pri etz hadar, כפות תמרים, kapot
tmarim, no ו vav connects them, כפות תמרים וענף עץ עבות וערבי
נחל. kapot tmarim ve-anaf etz avot ve-arvei nachal. So those three come
together. Also the idea that we have, we make the ברכה על
נטילת לולב, al netilat lulav, right, when we don't say על נטילת
ארבע מינים, al netilat arba minim, על נטילת אתרוג. al netilat etrog.
Why do we say על נטילת לולב? al netilat lulav? So first
of all because the לולב lulav. bunched together is three-quarters of the
job, of the deal, but still why mention the לולב? lulav So
the basic answer is because the לולב lulav is the tallest and
therefore it is the most dominant. And also it can connect to
the פסוק pasuk because the פסוק pasuk starts with כפות תמרים kapot
tmarim plus this plus that. But the center is כפות תמרים לולב.
kapot tmarim lulav. So here what we're saying is the same therefore
is true of the שיעור. shier. The minimum size of the לולב
Lulav has to be more than the minimum size of the הדס
hadas and the ערבה arava to allow for the fact that it
will stick out of the bundle. Now here's an interesting question. Let's
say you've exceeded the minimum. I have a five טפח לולב tefach
lulav but a six טפח ערבה. tefach arava. Can I put the
ערבה arava higher than the לולב? Lulav? Okay, cause they both satisfied
the minimum. And again, הלכתית halachically you can, but we do it
so that you actually situate them lower, you make sure that the
top of the לולב Lulav is going up from higher than the
bundle. Okay, so that's what he's saying. The minimum of those is
three and the לולב Lulav. is four, so the לולב Lulav should
go a טפח tefach higher. ורב פרנך
אמר רבי יוחנן Ve-Rav Parnach amar Rabbi Yochanan and רב פרנך Rav
Parnach says in the name of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, שדרה של
לולב צריך שייצא מן ההדס טפח. shidra shel lulav tzarich she-yeitzei min
ha-hadas tefach. It's not the tip of the leaves of the לולב,
Lulav the spine of the לולב Lulav has to be a טפח
tefach higher, okay, which really is
a more demanding requirement. Now notice this is the point I was
saying, it's not like you בדיעבד bediavad wouldn't be יוצא, yotzei, but
you go ahead and you have your מינים minim, and everything is
the minimum size. He's saying you have to make sure, he's not
talking about minimum sizes, he's saying when you bundle them together you
have to make sure that the spine goes a טפח tefach higher.
Okay that's interesting because some people might not make sure the spine,
they might have the top leaves going higher, he actually is demanding
that the spine goes a טפח tefach higher and something to pay
attention to when you're making your לולב. lulav Okay. תנן, Tnan, we
taught in a משנה. mishna. לולב שיש בו ג' טפחים כדי לנענע
בו כשר. Lulav she-yesh bo gimel tfachim kedai lenane'ah bo kosher. If
the לולב lulav is three טפחים tfachim to shake it,
it's כשר. kasher. So didn't you אביי Abaye just get to, I'm
sorry, רב יהודה אמר שמואל Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel just get through
saying it needs to have four טפחים? tfachim? Why does the משנה
mishna say three טפחים? tfachim? So אימא eima you should read it
וכדי לנענע בו כשר, u-khdai lenane'ah bo kosher, if it has and
enough to shake it, it is כשר, meaning it's three טפחים tfachim
plus an extra amount to shake it. מר כי איתליה ומר כי
איתליה. Mar ki-islei u-Mar ki-islei.
Each one like they said, which is רב יהודה אמר שמואל Rav
Yehuda amar Shmuel would say does not say that the spine has
to exceed, so according to him it's enough that the top of
the לולב lulav. is an extra טפח, tefach, and according to the
second opinion of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan who says that the spine
has to exceed, he would actually say that the spine even though
the spine would have to be. in order to, that would have
to be the extra amount כדי לנענע. k'dei l'nan'ei'ah. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara continues, תא
שמע, Ta Shma, come and hear. שיעור הדס וערבה שלושה, Shiur hadas
va'aravah shlosha, the size of a הדס Hadas and an ערבה Aravah
is three טפחים, Tefachim, ולולב ארבעה, ve'lulav arba'ah, and the לולב lulav.
is four טפחים. Tefachim. So מה לאו בהדי עלין, mah lav bahadei
alin, doesn't that mean going, you know, including the leaves, the whole
לולב? lulav And again, that's a proof to the first opinion and
it's against רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan who says that the spine has
to exceed a טפח, Tefach, and if the spine has to exceed,
so then you're measuring four טפחים Tefachim from the spine? לאו לבד
מעלין, lo l'vad me'alin, he would say it means you're counting the
four טפחים Tefachim of the spine, not the leaves. Okay, גופא. Gufa.
So now we have an interesting point. The משנה Mishna says three
טפחים. Tefachim. We have two אמוראic Amora statements that say four טפחים,
Tefachim, both of them reading the משנה Mishna three plus כדי לנענע,
k'dei l'nan'ei'ah, not three in order כדי לנענע, k'dei l'nan'ei'ah, three plus
a טפח, Tefach, and then they debate whether we're talking about the
whole לולב including the tops of the leaves has to be four
טפחים Tefachim or even just the spine has to be four טפחים.
Tefachim. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara goes on, גופא, Gufa, let's
get back to the basic statement of the size of the הדס
Hadas and the ערבה. Aravah.
שיעור הדס וערבה שלושה, Shiur hadas va'aravah shlosha, the minimum size of
the הדס Hadas and the ערבה Aravah is three. Did I skip
a line?
No. גופא. Gufa.
שיעור הדס וערבה שלושה, Shiur hadas va'aravah shlosha, הלולב ארבעה. ha'lulav arba'ah.
רבי טרפון אומר באמה בת חמישה טפחים. Rabbi Tarfon omer be'amah bat
chamisha tefachim. We're talking about an אמה Amah of five טפחים. Tefachim.
Now one way to read that is he's saying three טפחים Tefachim
isn't enough, you need it to be five טפחים. Tefachim. So אמר
רבא, Amar Rava, so רבא said שרא ליה מריה לרבי טרפון, Shara
lei marei l'Rabbi Tarfon, his master should forgive his master, meaning the
ריבונו של עולם Ribbono Shel Olam should forgive רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon
for saying such a thing. השתא עבוד שלושה לא משכחינן, Hashta avud
shlosha lo meshkachinan, we have a hard enough time finding three טפחים
Tefachim of braided leaves, right? Anybody ever like, you know, checked the
הדסים, Hadasim, you know you have to get all three leaves coming
from the same point, and you gotta, if you gotta get that
three טפחים Tefachim down, that's like really hard. So we have an
impossible time just getting three טפחים Tefachim of braided leaves. So בת
חמישה מיבעיא? bat chamisha miba'aya? Do you think we could get a
five טפח Tefach הדס? Hadas? What are you talking about? So the
גמרא Gemara says כי אתא רב דימי אמר, ki ata Rav Dimi
amar, when רב דימי Rav Dimi came from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
he explained it the following way. It doesn't mean you need a
five טפח Tefach הדס. Hadas. It means the following. אמה בת שישה
טפחים, Amah bat shisha tefachim, take your normal six טפח אמה, tefach
amah עביד אותה בת חמישה avid otah bat chamisha but subdivide it
into five. So if you take a six טפח אמה tefach amah,
and you subdivide it into five, each טפח Tefach is now a
טפח Tefach and a fifth. Okay, is that clear? Yes, okay. So
what he means is he doesn't say disagree with the three and
the four. He agrees, three for הדס Hadas and ערבה, Aravah, four
for לולב. But the question is how big are the טפחים Tefachim
you're measuring them with? So he says measure them with a five
טפח Tefach אמה. Amah, צאי מהם שלושה להדס והשאר ללולב. Tsei meihem
shlosha la'hadas ve'hashar la'lulav. What he means is we can agree that
your הדס Hadas here, let's draw that out of your הדס, Hadas,
your הדס Hadas here is three טפחים Tefachim and your לולב is
four, maybe four of the spine or four with the leaves, that's
the question of the debate, do you measure the four from here
or the four from here? But your לולב is four. He agrees
to the three and the four, he just says when you're coming
to measure these טפחים Tefachim don't measure it with a normal. Take
an אמה Amah of six טפחים, Tefachim, one two three four five
six, take a six טפח Tefach אמה Amah. and re-divide it into
five. So if you're going to re-divide it into five each one,
whatever, you get the idea, each טפח Tefach here is going to
be a טפח Tefach and a fifth. So take a, do a
five division of an אמה Amah not a six division, so you
actually get one point two, and use those types of טפחים Tefachim
to measure your, you know, to measure your לולב and your הדס.
Hadas. Okay, so that's what he is saying. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this, כמה הוי להו? kama havei lehu? תלתא ותלתא חומשי?
tlata ve'tlata chumshi? Okay, so then how much would you demand for
your הדס Hadas if each טפח Tefach is one point two? Your
הדס Hadas is going to have to be three and three-fifths, three
point six. So קשיא דשמואל אדשמואל, kashya de'Shmuel ad'Shmuel, then שמואל Shmuel
contradicts himself. הכא אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל hacha amar Rav Yehuda
amar Shmuel שיעור הדס וערבה שלושה, shiur hadas va'aravah shlosha, we started
by saying that they said that the הדס Hadas and the ערבה
Aravah have to be three טפחים. Tefachim. והתם, ve'hatam, and in another
place a little bit later in the גמרא Gemara we're about to
say, אמר רב הונא אמר שמואל amar Rav Huna amar Shmuel הלכה
כרבי טרפון, halacha k'Rabbi Tarfon, we rule like רבי טרפון. Rabbi Tarfon.
So if רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon means use a one point two
טפח, Tefach a טפח Tefach that's really one point two, and he's
really saying it has to be three point six, how can שמואל
Shmuel say that it has to be three? So the גמרא Gemara
says לא דק. lo dak. All right, when he said three he
wasn't being precise. גמרא Gemara says wait a minute. אימא דאמרינן לא
דק, eima de'amrinan lo dak, when would we say that he wasn't
being precise? If you can't you're not being precise לחומרא, l'chumra, if
you're rounding up to be strict. לקולא מי אמרינן? l'kula mi amrinan?
If you really demand 3.6, would not be imprecise and say 3?
Says מי אמרינן לא דק? mi amrinan lo dak? We would never
say לא דק lo dak to be lenient. You know, כי אתא
רבין, ki ata Ravin, so fine, let's do try another approach at
what this five thing, five טפח Tefach, אמה Amah means. So כי
אתא רבין אמר, ki ata Ravin amar, when רבין Ravin came, he
said the following: It means the opposite, well not the opposite, but
like the flip of what you were saying. אמה בת חמישה טפחים,
amah bat chamishah tefachim, take a five טפח Tefach אמה, Amah a
short אמה, amah, עשה אותו שישה, aseh oto shishah, and divide five
טפחים tefachim by six. Okay? So as opposed to here where you're
taking six טפחים tefachim and divide by five and you get a
1.2 טפח tefach אמה, amah, that's what we've been saying, now he
says: No no no, do the opposite. Start with a shorter אמה,
amah, an אמה amah of five, okay? And then divide that into
six units. So each טפח tefach is going to now be 5/6
of a טפח. tefach. And use a 5/6 טפח tefach to do
this measurement. Okay? Which is a nice קולא. kula. So let's take
a look. It says instead of 1.2 טפח... tefach... What? 5/6 of
a 1.2? No no no, 5/6 of a normal one טפח. tefach.
Take a yardstick that's five טפחים tefachim big, five normal טפחים tefachim
big and divide it by six. So you have a 5/6 of
a טפח. tefach. Okay? So he says תלתא מנייהו להדס, tlata mineihu
l'hadas, use three for the הדס, hadas, והשאר ללולב. v'hash'ar l'lulav. Now
if that's true, so הדס hadas has to only be three 5/6
טפחים, tefachim, so that's 15/6 which is 2.5, right? Okay, you see
the math? So that actually is a very important הלכה, halacha, that
you really only need 2.5 טפחים tefachim of the הדס, hadas, and
because it is so hard to find the הדס hadas with the
three leaves together, this actually becomes a- You can get a הדס
hadas that's longer, but how much of it has to be three
leaves together? So this actually gets us to 2.5, which makes things
definitely easier. So כמה הוו להו? kama havu lehu? So how much
then is the הדס hadas really required? תרי ופלגא, trei u'palga, two
and a half. Right? סוף סוף קשיא דשמואל אדשמואל. sof sof kashya
d'Shmuel a'd'Shmuel. Okay, then why does שמואל Shmuel say three? So גמרא
says לא דק. lo dak. והיינו לחומרא לא דק, v'hainu l'chumra lo
dak, he wasn't being precise and he was rounding up. He was
saying three instead of two and a half. That you're allowed to
say. דאמר רב הונא אמר שמואל, d'amar Rav Huna amar Shmuel, and
now we finally get to the statement we were referring to, הלכה
כרבי טרפון, halacha k'Rabbi Tarfon, because he says like רבי טרפון. Rabbi
Tarfon. How does that work with three? So we have רבי טרפון
Rabbi Tarfon meaning really two and a half and then he's rounding
up. So we're dealing with an unclear statement of רבי טרפון Rabbi
Tarfon that we've now redefined to say that it means use 5/6
טפח tefach טפחים. tefachim. Okay, let's get started on the next משנה,
mishna, but that was as you might imagine very important להלכה, l'halacha,
the idea of the split top leaf, of the bending, the issue
about the other split leaves, you know, and then the question about
the minimum size and how we accurately say three and four but
then we translate it to using short טפחים tefachim which makes it
more lenient, and the issue that again that we just said about
the לולב going higher than the other מינים, minim. and this issue
about are you measuring the לולב the entire one or are you
measuring it specifically about the spine, which makes even a higher- a
longer demand if you're measuring the spine rather than the entire לולב.
Okay, now we move on to the הדס. hadas. Okay? And we're
going to go through all of the ארבעה מינים, arba'ah minim, and
the משניות mishnayot are going to be structured almost the exact same
with local differences for each of the four מינים. Okay? So let's
take a look. הדס הגזול והיבש פסול. hadas ha'gazul v'ha'yavesh pasul. If
it's stolen or dried it's invalid. של אשירה ושל עיר הנדחת פסול.
shel asherah v'shel ir ha'nidachat pasul. So if it was worshipped as
an אשירה asherah or עיר הנדחת it's פסול. pasul, So we're not
going to have to discuss that because that's just a simple application
of whatever we said by לולב. נקטם ראשו, נפרצו עליו, niktam rosho,
nifretzu alav, if its head was cut off or its leaves fell
off, או שהיו ענביו מרובות מעליו, o she'hayu anavav merubot me'alav, and
here's a new idea, or if there were more berries than leaves
because on a הדס hadas it can grow berries, פסול, it's invalid.
ואם מיעטן כשר, v'im mi'atan kasher, if you pluck the berries and
now there are fewer berries than leaves, it's כשר. ואין ממעטין ביום
טוב, v'ein mematin b'Yom Tov, but you cannot pluck the berries on
יום טוב, Yom Tov, and we'll discuss why that is. One thing
to mention is it does not speak about like the לולב if
the leaves are fanned out, bind them together and so on because
you don't have that reality by a הדס. hadas. By a הדס
hadas what could happen to the leaves? They could fall off. They're
not going to spread out, they're not going to split, right? So
those realities you don't have, but you have a new reality of
the issue of the berries and that's the special case that's dealt
with. תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, and now this גמרא gets to this
issue of identifying what is the הדס, hadas, and here really I
remind you of what I said before like according to the רמב"ם,
Rambam, that we can assume they knew it by מסורה, masorah, they
had a tradition. ענף עץ עבות, anaf etz avot, okay, a branch
of braided wood, שענפיו חופין את עצו. she'anavav chofin et etzo. So
first we say that the ענף anaf has to be- the leaves
have to cover up the stick. And what is one like this?
הוי אומר זה הדס. Hevei omer zeh hadas. It's the הדס. hadas.
So the גמרא says, תימא זיתא? teima zeita? How about an olive
branch? The leaves cover up the branch? So no, בעינן עבות וליכא.
be'inan avot veleka. You need it to come in braids. The leaves
have to come in braids. They don't do that by an olive
tree. ותימא דולבא? Veteima dulba? How about the tree called a דולבא?
dulba? רש"י says it's an עץ ערמון, etz armon, which is what?
A chestnut? Okay. Chestnut. Oh no, olive was before. So the גמרא
says, okay, so there the leaves are braided. So the גמרא says
no, בעינן ענפיו חופין את עצו. be'inan anafav chofin et etzo. That
has the other problem. That might have braided leaves, but they don't
cover the branch. וליכא. Veleka. ותימא הירדוף? Veteima hirduf? How about הירדוף,
hirduf, which is another type of a thing that has braided leaves
which do cover the branch but apparently are very have thorns on
them or are very spiky, the leaves, and cause, you know, and
and will cause cuts. So what about that? So אמר אביי, Amar
Abaye, so like we said before, דרכיה דרכי נעם וליכא. deracheha darchei
noam veleka. You need it to be beautiful. The Torah would not
demand, the Torah's ways are pleasant, would not demand us to take
one of the ארבע מינים that would cut our hands. רבא אמר
מהכא, Rava amar mehacha, האמת והשלום אהבו, ha'emet vehashalom ehavu, love peace
and truth. And רש"י is saying, this isn't peace and I don't
know what you know if it's going to wind up cutting your
hand. Okay, interesting why he felt the need to quote another פסוק.
pasuk. Anyway, as I said, did they really not know and really
figure it out this way, or do we assume they always had
the tradition and we're just backwards connecting it and seeing how it
can be inferred from the verse? תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, our rabbis
taught. You know what? We'll end here. So, to be continued on
שבת. Shabbat. Okay.